<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2023-10-24T21:25:23+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ADA525  - Selva Kumar</title><subtitle>Webpage to contain necesary information and sourcefiles for the subject ADA525 @ HVL.</subtitle><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><entry><title type="html">Assignment 06: Input/Output</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_InputOutput/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 06: Input/Output" /><published>2023-10-24T22:32:51+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-24T22:32:51+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_InputOutput</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_InputOutput/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-introduction">1 Introduction</h1>
<p>Intro hva skal gjøres?</p>

<h1 id="2-input">2 Input</h1>
<p>sadasd
komponenter
input?
code</p>

<h1 id="3-output">3 Output</h1>
<p>output
code
sad</p>

<h1 id="7-evaluation-and-lesson-learned">7 Evaluation and lesson learned</h1>
<p>asd</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 Introduction Intro hva skal gjøres?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 05: Prototype 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_Prototype1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 05: Prototype 1" /><published>2023-10-10T17:05:11+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-10T17:05:11+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_Prototype1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_Prototype1/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-the-project">1 The Project</h1>
<p>As previously outlined in earlier project updates, I’m in the process of developing a laser gun game. This project encompasses 3D printed components, as well as electronics featuring the Arduino Uno R4 equipped with an ESP32 chip for wireless functionality. In this update, we’ll delve into the game’s design, development, and installation processes to achieve a functional prototype.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/28gjD4F/Updated-mode.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Updated Project Outline" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/28gjD4F/Updated-mode.png">here</a></p>

<h1 id="2-components">2 Components</h1>
<p>This project contains 3 main parts:</p>
<ul>
  <li>House</li>
  <li>Electronics</li>
  <li>Gun</li>
</ul>

<p>Originally, I intended to print three houses. However, due to challenges with the 3D printer and filament, I’ve opted to use just one house as the target for the game. Given that this course necessitates the creation of a prototype, a single house will suffice for that objective.</p>

<h2 id="21-house">2.1 House</h2>
<p>The house is printed in 3 parts (Main, door and roof). A final model is shown below (without the roof)</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/dKW3shQ/379588405-313593144690098-1661230860431114478-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Final Result" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/dKW3shQ/379588405-313593144690098-1661230860431114478-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<h2 id="22-electronics">2.2 Electronics</h2>
<p>For this project, I aimed to keep things straightforward, leading to my choice of the Arduino module. Initially, I had planned to use the Arduino Uno R3, complemented by an additional shield for ESP32 support. Fortunately, Arduino recently launched their new R4 version, which comes with an integrated ESP32 chip, saving me significant time. Currently, I’m awaiting the delivery of this module. The image displayed on this page showcases the earlier R3 version. For development, I’ll be utilizing VSCode in conjunction with PlatformIO. The latter is a sophisticated development environment tailored for microcontrollers, offering a broader range of functionalities compared to the Arduino IDE. It’s compatible with multiple operating systems and seamlessly integrates with various code editors, notably Microsoft’s Visual Studio Code. Unlike the Arduino IDE, PlatformIO boasts features like auto-complete, debugging, and eliminates the need for manual port selection. This tool streamlines the setup and coding process for diverse microcontrollers, including the Arduino Uno and ESP32.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/g6KYVm6/387530896-582262480636953-8679755345396056296-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Final Result" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/g6KYVm6/387530896-582262480636953-8679755345396056296-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/KwwdKnF/379660756-1700731580425402-4610422125662163263-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Final Result" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/KwwdKnF/379660756-1700731580425402-4610422125662163263-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<h2 id="23-gun">2.3 Gun</h2>
<p>For the Gun im going to find a toygun and modify it so that it shoots laser towards the target. If this should be challanging for the time being, im open to just use a laser pointer to demonstrate the purpose and keep it as an MVP solution (Minimum-Viable-Product).</p>

<p>[ IMG GUN ]</p>

<h1 id="3-laser-game">3 Laser Game</h1>
<p>As previously mentioned in my project updates, I’m developing a laser gun game that combines 3D printed components with advanced electronics, specifically the Arduino Uno R4 equipped with an ESP32 chip for wireless capabilities. The core mechanism of the game involves the laser gun emitting a high-powered light beam or laser, which is directed towards a light sensor strategically placed on a target inside the house. When the target is successfully hit by the laser, the player is awarded points.</p>

<p>Given that I ended up with a single house/target due to unforeseen challenges, I’ve had to think creatively about how to showcase various game modes. One approach I’m considering is to randomize both the intervals at which the door opens and the duration it remains open, revealing the target. This variability will introduce an element of unpredictability and challenge for the player.</p>

<p>To enhance the user experience, I’m also developing a web-app that will allow players to monitor their scores and adjust game settings. This integration not only offers real-time feedback but also provides a platform for potential future enhancements and game modes.</p>

<h1 id="4-fabrication-method-evaluation">4 Fabrication Method Evaluation</h1>
<p>I utilized 3D printing techniques to create a tangible model of the house. In my opinion, 3D printing is currently the most efficient and rapid method for producing parts. For enclosing the electronics, I believe 3D printing would also be the optimal approach. However, since I bypassed that exercise, I’m now inclined to use a laser-cut enclosure to showcase proficiency in that technique. In terms of challenges, I encountered some with my printer. Interestingly, the printer itself functioned well; the primary issue arose with the filament.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn.discordapp.com/attachments/1145664828199948359/1156140916160090155/IMG_5502.jpg?ex=65377c22&amp;is=65250722&amp;hm=767c4525881ae4e4bc1ec2ef9007a6a4d50b3c82b18e324db8449e33622d460c&amp;" alt="Project Outline" title="Final Result" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://cdn.discordapp.com/attachments/1145664828199948359/1156140916160090155/IMG_5502.jpg?ex=65377c22&amp;is=65250722&amp;hm=767c4525881ae4e4bc1ec2ef9007a6a4d50b3c82b18e324db8449e33622d460c&amp;">here</a></p>

<p>I also attempted to clean the nozzle and went through the process of unloading and reloading the filament, but to no avail. This situation proved to be a valuable learning experience for me. I had to extensively research solutions to the problem. I’m a firm believer in hands-on learning, and I think challenges like these, where things don’t go as planned, offer the best opportunities for growth and understanding.</p>

<p>Regarding the electronics, I plan to design a custom shield using a breadboard, which should seamlessly fit into the enclosure. Additionally, I’ve procured other electronic components, such as a light sensor and servo motor, specifically for this project.</p>

<h2 id="5-missing-components">5 Missing Components</h2>
<p>At present, I don’t find myself lacking any components or facing ambiguity regarding the game and its associated elements. While I haven’t received all the components for the project, they are en route, and I anticipate their arrival shortly. This proactive approach ensures that I’m well-prepared to move forward with the project as soon as all the necessary parts are in hand.</p>

<h1 id="6-todo">6 Todo</h1>
<p>Remaining Tasks for Project Completion</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Installing Step Motor Inside the House:</strong> I plan to use hot glue for this prototype. However, for the final product, I would redesign the house to incorporate a holder for the servo motor.</li>
  <li><strong>Final Electronics Wiring Diagram:</strong> While I currently have a clear understanding of the wiring, a comprehensive diagram still needs to be drafted.</li>
  <li><strong>Light Sensor Placement:</strong> The light sensor will be glued to the target inside the house.</li>
  <li><strong>Arduino R4 Shield Creation:</strong> A custom shield with the necessary electronics will be designed for the Arduino R4.</li>
  <li><strong>Arduino Code Development:</strong> With my proficiency in C programming, I have a clear roadmap for the coding process.</li>
  <li><strong>Web-App Development:</strong> A web-app will be created to facilitate communication with the ESP32.</li>
  <li><strong>Electronics Enclosure Design:</strong> An enclosure will be designed to house all the electronic components.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="7-evaluation-and-lesson-learned">7 Evaluation and lesson learned</h1>
<p>Throughout the development of the laser gun game, several key lessons emerged that have significantly shaped my approach to problem-solving and project management. The challenges faced with 3D printing, particularly with the filament, underscored the importance of adaptability and persistence. While 3D printing is a powerful tool for rapid prototyping, it’s not without its intricacies, and understanding its nuances is crucial. The filament issue, coupled with the need to extensively research solutions, reinforced the idea that hands-on learning is often the most impactful. Encountering obstacles and actively seeking solutions not only deepens one’s understanding but also hones troubleshooting skills. Additionally, the decision to pivot from a 3D printed enclosure to a laser-cut one highlighted the value of versatility in design and the importance of mastering multiple techniques. In the realm of electronics, designing a custom shield and integrating various components taught me the significance of meticulous planning and the need to anticipate potential integration challenges. In essence, this project has been a testament to the fact that while challenges are inevitable in any endeavor, they often pave the way for the most profound learning experiences.</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 The Project As previously outlined in earlier project updates, I’m in the process of developing a laser gun game. This project encompasses 3D printed components, as well as electronics featuring the Arduino Uno R4 equipped with an ESP32 chip for wireless functionality. In this update, we’ll delve into the game’s design, development, and installation processes to achieve a functional prototype.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 04: Digital Fabrication Recitation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_DigFab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 04: Digital Fabrication Recitation" /><published>2023-10-06T10:31:28+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-06T10:31:28+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_DigFab</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_DigFab/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-digital-fabrication-recitation">1. Digital Fabrication Recitation</h1>

<p>The fusion of digital and physical realms provides unprecedented opportunities for innovation and creativity in today’s swiftly evolving technological environment. As I began my voyage through the realm of digital fabrication, I found myself at the intersection of traditional craftsmanship and contemporary technology. The experience was a deep dive into the intricacies of digital design, fabrication techniques, and the tangible realization of concepts. This essay is a record of my experiences, lessons learned, and insights gained during this transformative voyage.</p>

<h1 id="2-website-development-and-its-consequences">2. Website Development and Its Consequences</h1>
<p>The introduction to the world of digital fabrication began with the ostensibly straightforward task of website creation. At first glance, creating a website may appear to be a simple task, particularly in this age of abundant digital platforms and tools. However, the process was considerably more complicated than I had anticipated. As described on my solution page, the voyage exemplified the evolving nature of the digital tools at our disposal.
The introduction to GitHub represented a turning point in this voyage. Previously, I believed that website development was a field designated for experienced programmers and developers. Nonetheless, GitHub introduced me to a platform that democratized the procedure. It offered a structured and collaborative environment that enabled the seamless integration of ideas and content. In addition to code management, it offered version control, collaboration features, and website hosting and publication. I had not previously conceived of this capability, which bridges the divide between ideas and their digital representation.</p>

<p>The technicalities were only one side of the argument. The difficulty lied in the realm of concepts. As the course’s trajectory was still taking shape and the instructor’s website was incomplete, I was forced to navigate a sea of uncertainty. Using my experience in product and electronic development, I conceived of a laser firing game. This ambitious undertaking appeared feasible within the course’s time constraints. The process of creating a website highlighted the significance of meticulous planning, adaptability, and foresight. It was a lesson in translating abstract concepts into tangible digital content, ensuring that the website not only functioned but also reflected my vision and objectives. The task also highlighted the importance of user experience and interface design. A website, after all, is not just a digital space but an interactive platform for users. I struggled with balancing aesthetics with functionality, assuring seamless navigation, and developing engaging content. This procedure emphasized the multidisciplinary character of website development, integrating design principles, technical expertise, and a thorough comprehension of the target audience.
The website development assignment was an exercise in narrative, design, and digital craftsmanship. It provided a platform for articulating ideas, showcasing projects, and engaging with a larger audience, emphasizing the transformative power of digital platforms in the interconnected world of today.</p>

<h1 id="3-cad-designing-bridging-the-digital-and-physical">3. CAD Designing: Bridging the Digital and Physical</h1>
<p>The transition to CAD design marked a significant turning point in my voyage with digital fabrication. While website development was about creating a digital presence, CAD designing was about conceptualizing tangible, real-world objects in a digital space. The task of devising multiple components for my project was both thrilling and difficult, a dance between my imagination and the limitations of reality.</p>

<p>My CAD solution page provides a thorough analysis of these experiences. Every design began with a concept, a notion of how a component should appear and operate. However, translating these ideas into digital models required a comprehensive comprehension of the software, design principles, and intended materials. Here is where I began to truly appreciate the capabilities that CAD design offered me. Before committing to physical production, the ability to conceptualize, modify, and perfect designs in a digital environment was revolutionary. It enabled a level of precision and iteration that would have been impractical, if not impossible, with conventional design methodologies. With these capabilities came obstacles. 
The infinite possibilities of the digital domain occasionally collided with the constraints of the physical world. Materials have characteristics, assets, and limitations. For instance, a design that appears flawless on-screen may be too fragile when printed or may not account for the subtleties of the material’s texture and behavior under various conditions. This digital-to-physical relationship became the primary focus of my CAD design experience. It was a constant reminder that, although digital tools offer tremendous flexibility, they must always be utilized with an awareness of real-world limitations.
Several redesigns were required to ensure that the components were not only functional but also optimized for 3D printing. This process of optimization was a lesson in efficiency and flexibility. Every modification and minute spent refining the design contributed to achieving a balance between aesthetic appeal, functionality, and manufacturability. It highlighted the significance of iterative design, wherein each iteration brings the digital model closer to its ideal physical equivalent.
CAD design taught me the complexities of working with various materials and manufacturing processes. Each material, whether plastic, metal, or wood, presents its own unique challenges and characteristics. Designing for 3D printing differs drastically from designing for laser cutting or conventional manufacturing techniques. Each technique has its own considerations, including material thickness, tolerances, and finishing methods. CAD designing was not just about creating digital models; it was about comprehending the intricate dance between the digital and physical realms. Each design challenge carried with it new learnings and insights, highlighting the transformative potential of CAD in the fabrication world.</p>

<h1 id="4-3d-printing-laser-cutting-and-the-realities-of-fabrication">4. 3D Printing, Laser Cutting, and the Realities of Fabrication</h1>
<p>The experience of 3D printing, often lauded as the poster child of modern fabrication, was revolutionary. With its promise of transforming digital designs into physical objects, the technology was both awe-inspiring and humbling. Observing a design come to life layer by layer for the first time was akin to witnessing a small miracle. The capability of the technology to materialize intricate designs, which would be difficult or even impossible with conventional methods, demonstrated its revolutionary potential.</p>

<p>As with any technology, 3D printing presented its own set of obstacles. Observing a design materialize was frequently marred by the complexities of the printing process. Constant considerations included ensuring print accuracy, maximizing material efficiency, and achieving functional integrity. The nozzle size of the printer, the melting point of the material, the print pace, and even the ambient temperature may all affect the outcome. It served as a stark reminder that, while digital designs provide a blueprint, the physical printing process introduces a vast number of variables.
The emphasis of the assignment on creating a multi-part design highlighted the capabilities and difficulties of 3D printing. While each component was designed to perfection in the digital sphere, real-world considerations such as print supports, material shrinkage, and post-processing requirements had to be considered. It was a lesson in the delicate equilibrium between design aesthetics, functionality, and fabrication realities. In contrast, laser cutting presented a unique set of challenges and opportunities. While I had enthusiastically anticipated this assignment, practical considerations led me to postpone it. The ambiguity surrounding the dimensions of my electronic components was a stark reminder of the significance of planning and foresight during the fabrication process. With its precision and speed, laser cutting offers enormous potential, particularly for creating intricate designs on materials such as wood, acrylic, and metal. However, it also necessitates meticulous planning, knowledge of material properties, and design considerations such as kerf width and material thermal sensitivity.</p>

<p>Additionally, the delayed laser cutting assignment highlighted the interconnected nature of the digital fabrication process. Each stage is interdependent, from CAD design to 3D printing to laser cutting. A modification or delay in a single step can have repercussions throughout the procedure. It highlighted the need for adaptability, tolerance, and a holistic understanding of the fabrication process. 3D printing and laser cutting were about navigating the intricate tango between digital designs and their physical manifestations, as opposed to simply producing objects. Each technology, with its distinctive capabilities and obstacles, provided invaluable insights into the art and science of digital fabrication.</p>

<h1 id="5-reflections-and-significant-insights">5. Reflections and Significant Insights</h1>
<p>Several key insights arise as I reflect on this transformative journey through digital fabrication, painting a comprehensive picture of the capabilities, challenges, and profound lessons derived from this experience.
Capabilities: The world of digital fabrication provided me with access to capabilities I had not previously envisaged. From the accuracy of CAD design to the materialization of concepts via 3D printing and laser cutting, the technology’s potential is extensive. It allows for greater customization, iteration, and innovation than conventional methods. Before committing to physical production, the ability to conceptualize, modify, and perfect designs in a digital environment has revolutionized the design and fabrication process.</p>

<p><strong>Digital-Physical Relationship:</strong> The intricate relationship between the digital and physical domains was one of the most profound insights. While digital tools offer an infinite number of possibilities, the real world imposes material, physical, and practical constraints. This connection was apparent at each stage, from CAD design to 3D fabrication. It emphasized the significance of understanding material properties, manufacturing techniques, and the subtleties involved in translating a digital design into a physical object.</p>

<p><strong>Practical Examples:</strong> The voyage was replete with instances in which the digital model deviated from the actual product. Whether it was a 3D print that required additional supports, a CAD design that required material efficiency adjustments, or laser cutting considerations, each deviation was a lesson in adaptability and problem solving.</p>

<p><strong>Limitations of Digital Design:</strong> While the digital domain offers unmatched precision and adaptability, it has also revealed the limitations of designing without a tactile understanding of the material. Traditional methods, like carpentry, allow for a hands-on approach, experiencing the material’s texture, grain, and response. In contrast, digital design, while potent, occasionally overlooks these nuances, highlighting the need for a balance between digital precision and practicality in the real world.</p>

<p><strong>Problem-Solving:</strong> The voyage did not lack obstacles. From design modifications to 3D printing optimization, problem-solving was a recurring theme. One difficulty was assuring the precision and material efficiency of 3D printing. This required a reevaluation of the CAD design, iteration, and testing. These obstacles, while occasionally daunting, provided invaluable lessons. They highlighted both the limitations and enormous benefits of digital fabrication, emphasizing the importance of adaptability, foresight, and a thorough knowledge of the available tools.</p>

<p>This journey through digital fabrication was more than a series of assignments; it was a transformative experience that transformed my understanding of design, fabrication, and the limitless opportunities that exist at the intersection of the digital and physical worlds. It was a testament to the effectiveness of experiential learning, where theoretical knowledge is brought to life through application. As I consider the future, I am filled with enthusiasm and eagerness, eager to continue investigating, learning, and pushing the boundaries of what is possible in this dynamic field.</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1. Digital Fabrication Recitation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 03: Laser Cutting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_Laser/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 03: Laser Cutting" /><published>2023-09-27T10:31:28+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-27T10:31:28+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_Laser</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_Laser/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-to-be-determined">1 To be determined…</h1>
<p>This is postponed to be demonstrated during development of Electronic Enclosre.</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 To be determined… This is postponed to be demonstrated during development of Electronic Enclosre.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 02: 3D Print</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_3DPrint/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 02: 3D Print" /><published>2023-09-09T10:31:28+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-09T10:31:28+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_3DPrint</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_3DPrint/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-the-3d-model">1 The 3D Model</h1>
<p>The project currently has three main components that need to be both 3D designed and printed. For efficiency, I’m considering making all the houses identical. Each house will consist of there parts: a door with hinges and the house which i divided into bottom and top. The electronics will be housed in a shielded enclosure, which will also have two parts: a frame and a lid. 
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/82VZNvs/2-1.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h2 id="11-house-bottom">1.1 House (Bottom)</h2>
<p>This is the base of the house. I searched the internet for inspiration, looking for something simple. Initially, I considered a large house or wall that could interlock with others, but I realized it was unnecessary. Additionally, I wanted the ability to adjust the distance between my “targets” to make it challenging for users to aim quickly. The house has an opening for a door, and the roof is separate.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/HFTBMMs/2-2.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h2 id="12-house-top">1.2 House (Top)</h2>
<p>This is the top of the house, which functions like a hat. This design makes it easy to lift off, allowing for convenient access to work on the contents, such as attaching the servo, toy figure, and sensor.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/b5nFcKr/2-4.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h2 id="13-door">1.3 Door</h2>
<p>This is the movable part of the project. The door is held in place by a pin that goes through the “hinges” mounted on the house’s wall. The door is designed to open inward.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/NFgm4QW/2-3.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h1 id="2-from-cad-to-3d-print">2 From CAD to 3D print</h1>
<p>Before printing the parts, I needed to ensure that they fit together without any collisions, especially the connections between the door and the house.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/M9wrqrp/2-motion.gif" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<p>Given that this was my inaugural print, I opted for a wall thickness of 5mm to assess the sturdiness of the 3D prints. Fusion360 software conveniently supports a 3D printing setup, making it relatively straightforward to prepare a print.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/rcF3STx/3-2.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Fusion360" /></p>

<p>These are my settings to create STL-files for the 3D-printer.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/QYQmGZx/Skjermbilde-2023-09-21-kl-16-51-34.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Fusion360" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/QYQmGZx/Skjermbilde-2023-09-21-kl-16-51-34.png">here</a></p>

<h2 id="21-3d-print">2.1 3D Print</h2>
<p>To create the 3D print, I used Ultimaker 3 with PLA filaments in Black and White color. 
<img src="https://content.invisioncic.com/ultimake/monthly_2023_08/IMG_5729.JPEG.9dbee9d99f35694ee1d53e19f78565f7.JPEG" alt="Project Outline" title="Ultimaker3" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://content.invisioncic.com/ultimake/monthly_2023_08/IMG_5729.JPEG.9dbee9d99f35694ee1d53e19f78565f7.JPEG">here</a></p>

<p>I used the Ulitmaker Cura as my slicer for this project with these settings
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/wyMBmb3/3-0.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Ultimaker3" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/wyMBmb3/3-0.png">here</a></p>

<p>“Before beginning the printing process, I applied a glue pen to coat the printing plate. This step helps reduce the likelihood of the print adhering too firmly to the glass.</p>

<p>Below are some pictures of the progress.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/nj2Y960/379582427-671341501610531-2372527959637092926-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Progress" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/nj2Y960/379582427-671341501610531-2372527959637092926-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/5KNdLFr/381949127-269148839329034-2477637698480515237-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Progress" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/5KNdLFr/381949127-269148839329034-2477637698480515237-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/VMptxPd/379506468-226910486708972-2559037656850310393-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Progress" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/VMptxPd/379506468-226910486708972-2559037656850310393-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<h1 id="22-final-result">2.2 Final result</h1>
<p>Here is my final result</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/dKW3shQ/379588405-313593144690098-1661230860431114478-n.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Final Result" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/dKW3shQ/379588405-313593144690098-1661230860431114478-n.jpg">here</a></p>

<p><img src="https://cdn.discordapp.com/attachments/1145664828199948359/1153658100042190890/Selva_demo.webp" alt="Project Outline" title="FInal Result" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://cdn.discordapp.com/attachments/1145664828199948359/1153658100042190890/Selva_demo.webp">here</a></p>

<h1 id="3-evaluation-and-lesson-learned">3 Evaluation and lesson learned</h1>

<p>I found this exercise both enjoyable and enlightening, presenting numerous learning opportunities. The 3D printing aspect was particularly novel for me, and it quickly piqued my interest. During the printing process, I discovered that removing supports can be challenging. My door, being quite thin, sustained some damage when I attempted to remove its supports.</p>

<p>I also recognized the need to reduce the thickness of my walls to save on materials and decrease printing time. After assembling the initial print and testing all the components, I realized the necessity of adding a floor to the house to secure the electronics. I also made some adjustments to the roof’s measurements to conserve materials further.</p>

<p>Another observation was the difficulty in removing a 3D print when its bottom layer is solidly adhered to the printing plate, especially since the 3D model automatically settled in the slicer. For future prints, I plan to introduce a support layer at the bottom to facilitate easier removal.</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 The 3D Model The project currently has three main components that need to be both 3D designed and printed. For efficiency, I’m considering making all the houses identical. Each house will consist of there parts: a door with hinges and the house which i divided into bottom and top. The electronics will be housed in a shielded enclosure, which will also have two parts: a frame and a lid.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 01: CAD Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_Cad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 01: CAD Model" /><published>2023-09-08T23:26:04+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T23:26:04+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_Cad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_Cad/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-idea--conceptualizing">1 Idea &amp; Conceptualizing</h1>
<p>In my previous post, I already outlined the concept for my final project. While choosing the right project for this subject, I had to weigh several factors, including the learning objectives set by the course and how best to present my work to my professor. I began by reviewing the core components of the subject, which encompassed electronics, CAD, 3D printing, laser cutting, and web-app development. This led to extensive brainstorming on potential projects. Although I have a passion for prototyping and product development, I was cautious not to overextend the project’s scope.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/2WJz1GN/Skjermbilde-2023-08-28-111433.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Laser Gun Game" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/2WJz1GN/Skjermbilde-2023-08-28-111433.png">here</a></p>

<p>It was essential for my project to incorporate electronics, and I wanted parts that could move without overly complicating the design. This led me to choose servo motors. I then needed to select a central processing unit for the project, and I opted for the Arduino Uno. My choice was influenced by its foundation on the ATMega328P chip, which I am familiar with from my bachelor’s studies in electronics. Additionally, I have extensive experience using the Arduino Uno in past hobby projects.</p>

<p>Here is picture of Arduino Uno
<img src="https://knowhow.distrelec.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/iStock-458960107.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Arduino Uno" /></p>

<p>For movement, I decided to integrate four servo motors. These motors will control the appearance and disappearance of targets in my shooting game, adhering to a “keep-it-simple” philosophy. To detect hits on the targets, I plan to use a light sensor that can measure resistance levels when a light beam is detected.</p>

<p>I believe using this servo motor creates enough movement for my project
<img src="https://gpiocc.github.io/learn/assets/post/2020-04-10-martin-ku-control-a-servo-motor-with-arduino/servo-sweeping.gif" alt="Project Outline" title="Servo Motors" /></p>

<p>The initial design was too basic, and I realized that to secure a higher grade for this subject, I needed to enhance its complexity. Consequently, I’ve decided to use an ESP32 to create a web-app accessible via smartphones. This web-app will offer users the option to increase the challenge by adjusting the speed of the targets or altering the pattern in which targets become visible. By integrating the web-app, I can genuinely encompass all the primary learning objectives of the subject.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/28gjD4F/Updated-mode.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Updated Project Outline" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/28gjD4F/Updated-mode.png">here</a></p>

<h1 id="2-cad---the-visual-aspects">2 CAD - The Visual aspects</h1>
<p>My project involves creating a shooting game where shots are simulated with a laser gun. I’m not focusing much on the gun itself; instead, I’m directing my attention to the target that needs to be hit. This is where the electronics and movement of the target objects will be incorporated. I made this decision based on the time constraints.</p>

<p>Initially, I thought of constructing a large apartment block with four doors that could open. However, due to what I assume are limitations in 3D printer size, I’m now considering four identical houses placed at some distance from each other. I believe this will enhance the gaming experience as the objects can be positioned at varying distances from one another. Additionally, having identical house objects simplifies the CAD process. One of the houses will serve as the main unit, housing all the electronics. For now, the houses will be interconnected using cable connections.”
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/82VZNvs/2-1.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h2 id="21-main-parts">2.1 Main parts</h2>
<p>The project currently has three main components that need to be both 3D designed and printed. For efficiency, I’m considering making all the houses identical. Each house will consist of there parts: a door with hinges and the house which i divided into bottom and top. The electronics will be housed in a shielded enclosure, which will also have two parts: a frame and a lid.</p>

<h3 id="211-house-bottom">2.1.1 House Bottom</h3>
<p>This is the base of the house. I searched the internet for inspiration, looking for something simple. Initially, I considered a large house or wall that could interlock with others, but I realized it was unnecessary. Additionally, I wanted the ability to adjust the distance between my “targets” to make it challenging for users to aim quickly. The house has an opening for a door, and the roof is separate.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/HFTBMMs/2-2.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h3 id="212-house-top">2.1.2 House Top</h3>
<p>This is the top of the house, which functions like a hat. This design makes it easy to lift off, allowing for convenient access to work on the contents, such as attaching the servo, toy figure, and sensor.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/b5nFcKr/2-4.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h3 id="213-door">2.1.3 Door</h3>
<p>This is the movable part of the project. The door is held in place by a pin that goes through the “hinges” mounted on the house’s wall. The door is designed to open inward.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/NFgm4QW/2-3.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h3 id="214-targets">2.1.4 Targets</h3>
<p>The targets will likely be 3D models that I’ll source from the internet. After downloading these 3D assets, I’ll proceed directly to 3D printing.
This not determined at the moment.</p>

<h3 id="215-electronic-enclosure">2.1.5 Electronic Enclosure</h3>
<p>The electronic enclosure, which will accommodate the Arduino Uno, motor controls, and ESP32, will be designed after the circuit development is complete, as I’m uncertain about the appearance of the “shield” at this time.</p>

<h2 id="22-manufacturing-process">2.2 Manufacturing Process</h2>
<p>I’m planning for all components of this project to be 3D printed. At first, I considered laser-cutting the box for the electronics. However, I now believe that if I can 3D print it and attach it to the house, the overall product will look better. The house’s dimensions must be within the capabilities of the 3D printer, both in terms of width and height.</p>

<h2 id="23-external-components">2.3 External Components</h2>
<p>For external components, I’m considering using screws, glue to attach figures to the house, and electronics. Additionally, there will be accessories for the servo motor to facilitate movements, such as opening and closing the door. These are the primary elements I envision needing for the project. In my opinion, it’s too early to specify all the equipment required. Everything must be produced first to determine what I’ll need to complete the device.</p>

<h2 id="24-mechanical-movements">2.4 Mechanical Movements</h2>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the door will be opened and closed using a servo motor. The door has a mount on the back that the servo motor can attach to. This allows for the movement as shown below.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/M9wrqrp/2-motion.gif" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h1 id="3-evaluation-and-lesson-learned">3 Evaluation and lesson learned</h1>
<p>It felt a bit unusual for me to dive into CAD so early in the project, especially since I’m still in the brainstorming phase. My project is evolving, with details being continuously refined and expanded. Over the past week, I’ve decided to incorporate the ESP32 to achieve mobile web-app capabillities. I believe the workflow should have been approached in reverse. That’s why I’ve chosen to delay modeling the electronics box. I’m considering laser-cutting the box to ensure I’ve mastered that aspect of the subject as well.</p>

<p>When it came to creating the 3D CAD design, it was crucial for me to conduct some research first and settle on a design concept. I have some prior experience with 3D CAD and understand the importance of thoroughly thinking through the design before starting. This ensures the model’s axes are correctly aligned, making modifications easier down the line.</p>

<p>This was a relatively simple design. Typically, I brainstorm and sketch out by hand what I aim to design, visualizing its approximate appearance with some key dimensions. It’s also essential to decide how the model should be segmented to ensure the “parts” are correctly defined.</p>

<p>After that, I began drawing to see if the design worked as envisioned. Since I intended to 3D print this, I kept simplicity in mind throughout the design process.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 Idea &amp; Conceptualizing In my previous post, I already outlined the concept for my final project. While choosing the right project for this subject, I had to weigh several factors, including the learning objectives set by the course and how best to present my work to my professor. I began by reviewing the core components of the subject, which encompassed electronics, CAD, 3D printing, laser cutting, and web-app development. This led to extensive brainstorming on potential projects. Although I have a passion for prototyping and product development, I was cautious not to overextend the project’s scope. If the picture is not readable then use this link here]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 00: Plan and Sketch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_Plan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 00: Plan and Sketch" /><published>2023-08-28T10:29:20+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T10:29:20+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_Plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_Plan/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="project-initiation--web-setup">Project Initiation &amp; Web Setup</h1>

<p>I’ve successfully set up my website as specified by the project requirements. The live site is hosted on a custom webserver, and all source files are available on <a href="http://github.com/selvack/ada525/">GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2 id="setting-up-the-development-environment-on-mac">Setting Up the Development Environment on Mac</h2>
<p>Follow the steps below:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Install Homebrew:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>/bin/bash <span class="nt">-c</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">$(</span>curl <span class="nt">-fsSL</span> https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh<span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">"</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Install dependencies:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> brew <span class="nb">install </span>chruby ruby-install xz
 ruby-install ruby
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Configure chruby in ~/.zshrc:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"source </span><span class="si">$(</span>brew <span class="nt">--prefix</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">/opt/chruby/share/chruby/chruby.sh"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc
 <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"source </span><span class="si">$(</span>brew <span class="nt">--prefix</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">/opt/chruby/share/chruby/auto.sh"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc
 <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"chruby ruby-3.1.3"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc  <span class="c"># Replace with the current version after running 'chruby'.</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Restart the terminal, then:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> ruby <span class="nt">-v</span>  <span class="c"># To confirm the version.</span>
 gem <span class="nb">install </span>jekyll bundler
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="project-theme--setup">Project Theme &amp; Setup</h2>
<ol>
  <li>I used the <a href="https://github.com/piharpi/jekyll-klise">Klise</a>, a jekyll template for this project. To set it up:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># cd Documents/ada525    optional.</span>
jekyll ada525  <span class="c"># optional name ; i chose ADA525</span>
git clone https://github.com/piharpi/jekyll-klise.git
bundle <span class="nb">install
</span>bundle <span class="nb">exec </span>jekyll serve
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Access the local server via <a href="127.0.0.1:4000">127.0.0.1:4000</a> or <a href="localhost:4000">localhost:4000</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Edit the necessary files using <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a>. Note: Jekyll uses <a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/tools/jekyll/">Markdown</a> for text-to-HTML conversion.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="deploying-to-github">Deploying to GitHub</h2>
<p>Use these commands to push your local content to GitHub:</p>
<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>git init
git add <span class="nb">.</span> 
git commit <span class="nt">-m</span> <span class="s2">"Initial commit"</span>
git remote add origin https://github.com/selvack/ada525.git
git push origin main
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Since my selected jekyll themes plugin (jekyll-postfiles) isn’t supported by github pages, the site will encounter problems such as broken path or post images won’t show up. I chose therefor to host on my private web-server. 
To do so, upload this path to the site web-folder</p>
<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>./_site/
</code></pre></div></div>

<h4 id="-now-the-page-is-online-">** NOW THE PAGE IS ONLINE **</h4>
<p>private server url: <a href="https://ada525.intellico.no/">https://ada525.intellico.no/</a></p>

<hr />

<hr />

<h1 id="my-final-project-outline">My Final project outline</h1>
<p>For my final project, I intend to develop a laser gun game. The concept involves shooting lasers at target figures, designed to resemble infantry soldiers. Every successful hit will register and display a score on an integrated screen. The core of this project will likely be built around an Arduino circuit.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/2WJz1GN/Skjermbilde-2023-08-28-111433.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Laser Gun Game" /></p>

<h2 id="final-project-undecided-factors">Final Project: Undecided Factors</h2>
<p>As we continue to develop our project, several components remain undecided. Here’s a rundown of these aspects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Targets (Toy soldiers or Images)</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>The targets might have a movement mechanism.</li>
      <li><em>Thought:</em> Could a stepper motor be utilized to topple them when hit?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Display</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Choice between an LCD display or a Segment display for point tallying.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Sound</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Do we want to include sound effects?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>CAD Model for the Laser Gun</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>No design has been finalized for the gun.</li>
      <li><em>Strategy:</em> Perhaps modifying an existing gun design would expedite the process?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>CAD Model for Infantry Barricades</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Is there a need for house-like barricades?</li>
      <li><em>Idea:</em> Could we “animate” a door that opens, presenting soldiers to the shooter?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Variety in Soldier Types</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Should one soldier have a unique rank, serving as a ‘Boss’ character?</li>
      <li><em>Advantage:</em> Hitting this character could yield more points.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>2x Arduino in Serial Mode?</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>The Arduino Uno has only 6 IO analog pins. Given that we’re using 4 light-sensitive diodes and need an additional one for serial output to the display, this might pose a challenge. This limits the soldiers to be maximum 4 and 1 for LCD if im to incorporate sound effects.</li>
      <li>To incorporate sound effects, we may need to use two Arduino Unos in tandem. Alternatively, I might find a simpler solution that requires just one Arduino.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="initial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Project Initiation &amp; Web Setup]]></summary></entry></feed>