<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2023-09-12T20:25:50+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ADA525  - Selva Kumar</title><subtitle>Webpage to contain necesary information and sourcefiles for the subject ADA525 @ HVL.</subtitle><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><entry><title type="html">Assignment 02: 3D Print</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_3DPrint/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 02: 3D Print" /><published>2023-09-09T10:31:28+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-09T10:31:28+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_3DPrint</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_3DPrint/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-lezz-go">1 Lezz go</h1>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 Lezz go]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 01: CAD Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_Cad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 01: CAD Model" /><published>2023-09-08T23:26:04+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T23:26:04+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_Cad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_Cad/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-idea--conceptualizing">1 Idea &amp; Conceptualizing</h1>
<p>In my previous post, I already outlined the concept for my final project. While choosing the right project for this subject, I had to weigh several factors, including the learning objectives set by the course and how best to present my work to my professor. I began by reviewing the core components of the subject, which encompassed electronics, CAD, 3D printing, laser cutting, and web-app development. This led to extensive brainstorming on potential projects. Although I have a passion for prototyping and product development, I was cautious not to overextend the project’s scope.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/2WJz1GN/Skjermbilde-2023-08-28-111433.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Laser Gun Game" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/2WJz1GN/Skjermbilde-2023-08-28-111433.png">here</a></p>

<p>It was essential for my project to incorporate electronics, and I wanted parts that could move without overly complicating the design. This led me to choose servo motors. I then needed to select a central processing unit for the project, and I opted for the Arduino Uno. My choice was influenced by its foundation on the ATMega328P chip, which I am familiar with from my bachelor’s studies in electronics. Additionally, I have extensive experience using the Arduino Uno in past hobby projects.</p>

<p>Here is picture of Arduino Uno
<img src="https://knowhow.distrelec.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/iStock-458960107.jpg" alt="Project Outline" title="Arduino Uno" /></p>

<p>For movement, I decided to integrate four servo motors. These motors will control the appearance and disappearance of targets in my shooting game, adhering to a “keep-it-simple” philosophy. To detect hits on the targets, I plan to use a light sensor that can measure resistance levels when a light beam is detected.</p>

<p>I believe using this servo motor creates enough movement for my project
<img src="https://gpiocc.github.io/learn/assets/post/2020-04-10-martin-ku-control-a-servo-motor-with-arduino/servo-sweeping.gif" alt="Project Outline" title="Servo Motors" /></p>

<p>The initial design was too basic, and I realized that to secure a higher grade for this subject, I needed to enhance its complexity. Consequently, I’ve decided to use an ESP32 to create a web-app accessible via smartphones. This web-app will offer users the option to increase the challenge by adjusting the speed of the targets or altering the pattern in which targets become visible. By integrating the web-app, I can genuinely encompass all the primary learning objectives of the subject.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/28gjD4F/Updated-mode.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Updated Project Outline" />
If the picture is not readable then use this link <a href="https://i.ibb.co/28gjD4F/Updated-mode.png">here</a></p>

<h1 id="2-cad---the-visual-aspects">2 CAD - The Visual aspects</h1>
<p>My project involves creating a shooting game where shots are simulated with a laser gun. I’m not focusing much on the gun itself; instead, I’m directing my attention to the target that needs to be hit. This is where the electronics and movement of the target objects will be incorporated. I made this decision based on the time constraints.</p>

<p>Initially, I thought of constructing a large apartment block with four doors that could open. However, due to what I assume are limitations in 3D printer size, I’m now considering four identical houses placed at some distance from each other. I believe this will enhance the gaming experience as the objects can be positioned at varying distances from one another. Additionally, having identical house objects simplifies the CAD process. One of the houses will serve as the main unit, housing all the electronics. For now, the houses will be interconnected using cable connections.”
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/82VZNvs/2-1.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h2 id="21-main-parts">2.1 Main parts</h2>

<p>The project currently has two main components that need to be both 3D designed and printed. For efficiency, I’m considering making all the houses identical. Each house will consist of there parts: a door with hinges and the house which i divided into bottom and top. The electronics will be housed in a shielded enclosure, which will also have two parts: a frame and a lid.</p>

<p><strong>2.1.1 House Bottom</strong></p>

<p>This is the base of the house. I searched the internet for inspiration, looking for something simple. Initially, I considered a large house or wall that could interlock with others, but I realized it was unnecessary. Additionally, I wanted the ability to adjust the distance between my “targets” to make it challenging for users to aim quickly. The house has an opening for a door, and the roof is separate.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/HFTBMMs/2-2.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<p><strong>2.1.2 House Top</strong></p>

<p>This is the top of the house, which functions like a hat. This design makes it easy to lift off, allowing for convenient access to work on the contents, such as attaching the servo, toy figure, and sensor.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/b5nFcKr/2-4.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<p><strong>2.1.3 Door</strong></p>

<p>This is the movable part of the project. The door is held in place by a pin that goes through the “hinges” mounted on the house’s wall. The door is designed to open inward.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/NFgm4QW/2-3.png" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<p><strong>2.1.4 Targets</strong></p>

<p>The targets will likely be 3D models that I’ll source from the internet. After downloading these 3D assets, I’ll proceed directly to 3D printing.
This not determined at the moment.</p>

<p><strong>2.1.5 Electronic Enclosure</strong></p>

<p>The electronic enclosure, which will accommodate the Arduino Uno, motor controls, and ESP32, will be designed after the circuit development is complete, as I’m uncertain about the appearance of the “shield” at this time.</p>

<h2 id="22-manufacturing-process">2.2 Manufacturing Process</h2>
<p>I’m planning for all components of this project to be 3D printed. At first, I considered laser-cutting the box for the electronics. However, I now believe that if I can 3D print it and attach it to the house, the overall product will look better. The house’s dimensions must be within the capabilities of the 3D printer, both in terms of width and height.</p>

<h2 id="23-external-components">2.3 External Components</h2>
<p>For external components, I’m considering using screws, glue to attach figures to the house, and electronics. Additionally, there will be accessories for the servo motor to facilitate movements, such as opening and closing the door. These are the primary elements I envision needing for the project. In my opinion, it’s too early to specify all the equipment required. Everything must be produced first to determine what I’ll need to complete the device.</p>

<h2 id="24-mechanical-movements">2.4 Mechanical Movements</h2>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the door will be opened and closed using a servo motor. The door has a mount on the back that the servo motor can attach to. This allows for the movement as shown below.
<img src="https://i.ibb.co/M9wrqrp/2-motion.gif" alt="Project Outline" title="House" /></p>

<h1 id="3-evaluation-and-lesson-learned">3 Evaluation and lesson learned</h1>
<p>It felt a bit unusual for me to dive into CAD so early in the project, especially since I’m still in the brainstorming phase. My project is evolving, with details being continuously refined and expanded. Over the past week, I’ve decided to incorporate the ESP32 to achieve mobile web-app capabillities. I believe the workflow should have been approached in reverse. That’s why I’ve chosen to delay modeling the electronics box. I’m considering laser-cutting the box to ensure I’ve mastered that aspect of the subject as well.</p>

<p>When it came to creating the 3D CAD design, it was crucial for me to conduct some research first and settle on a design concept. I have some prior experience with 3D CAD and understand the importance of thoroughly thinking through the design before starting. This ensures the model’s axes are correctly aligned, making modifications easier down the line.</p>

<p>This was a relatively simple design. Typically, I brainstorm and sketch out by hand what I aim to design, visualizing its approximate appearance with some key dimensions. It’s also essential to decide how the model should be segmented to ensure the “parts” are correctly defined.</p>

<p>After that, I began drawing to see if the design worked as envisioned. Since I intended to 3D print this, I kept simplicity in mind throughout the design process.”</p>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="assignement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 Idea &amp; Conceptualizing In my previous post, I already outlined the concept for my final project. While choosing the right project for this subject, I had to weigh several factors, including the learning objectives set by the course and how best to present my work to my professor. I began by reviewing the core components of the subject, which encompassed electronics, CAD, 3D printing, laser cutting, and web-app development. This led to extensive brainstorming on potential projects. Although I have a passion for prototyping and product development, I was cautious not to overextend the project’s scope. If the picture is not readable then use this link here]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assignment 00: Plan and Sketch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/00_Plan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assignment 00: Plan and Sketch" /><published>2023-08-28T10:29:20+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T10:29:20+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/00_Plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/00_Plan/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="project-initiation--web-setup">Project Initiation &amp; Web Setup</h1>

<p>I’ve successfully set up my website as specified by the project requirements. The live site is hosted on a custom webserver, and all source files are available on <a href="http://github.com/selvack/ada525/">GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2 id="setting-up-the-development-environment-on-mac">Setting Up the Development Environment on Mac</h2>
<p>Follow the steps below:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Install Homebrew:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>/bin/bash <span class="nt">-c</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">$(</span>curl <span class="nt">-fsSL</span> https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh<span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">"</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Install dependencies:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> brew <span class="nb">install </span>chruby ruby-install xz
 ruby-install ruby
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Configure chruby in ~/.zshrc:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"source </span><span class="si">$(</span>brew <span class="nt">--prefix</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">/opt/chruby/share/chruby/chruby.sh"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc
 <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"source </span><span class="si">$(</span>brew <span class="nt">--prefix</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">/opt/chruby/share/chruby/auto.sh"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc
 <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"chruby ruby-3.1.3"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> ~/.zshrc  <span class="c"># Replace with the current version after running 'chruby'.</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Restart the terminal, then:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> ruby <span class="nt">-v</span>  <span class="c"># To confirm the version.</span>
 gem <span class="nb">install </span>jekyll bundler
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="project-theme--setup">Project Theme &amp; Setup</h2>
<ol>
  <li>I used the <a href="https://github.com/piharpi/jekyll-klise">Klise</a>, a jekyll template for this project. To set it up:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># cd Documents/ada525    optional.</span>
jekyll ada525  <span class="c"># optional name ; i chose ADA525</span>
git clone https://github.com/piharpi/jekyll-klise.git
bundle <span class="nb">install
</span>bundle <span class="nb">exec </span>jekyll serve
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Access the local server via <a href="127.0.0.1:4000">127.0.0.1:4000</a> or <a href="localhost:4000">localhost:4000</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Edit the necessary files using <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a>. Note: Jekyll uses <a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/tools/jekyll/">Markdown</a> for text-to-HTML conversion.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="deploying-to-github">Deploying to GitHub</h2>
<p>Use these commands to push your local content to GitHub:</p>
<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>git init
git add <span class="nb">.</span> 
git commit <span class="nt">-m</span> <span class="s2">"Initial commit"</span>
git remote add origin https://github.com/selvack/ada525.git
git push origin main
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Since my selected jekyll themes plugin (jekyll-postfiles) isn’t supported by github pages, the site will encounter problems such as broken path or post images won’t show up. I chose therefor to host on my private web-server. 
To do so, upload this path to the site web-folder</p>
<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>./_site/
</code></pre></div></div>

<h4 id="-now-the-page-is-online-">** NOW THE PAGE IS ONLINE **</h4>
<p>private server url: <a href="https://ada525.intellico.no/">https://ada525.intellico.no/</a></p>

<hr />

<hr />

<h1 id="my-final-project-outline">My Final project outline</h1>
<p>For my final project, I intend to develop a laser gun game. The concept involves shooting lasers at target figures, designed to resemble infantry soldiers. Every successful hit will register and display a score on an integrated screen. The core of this project will likely be built around an Arduino circuit.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.ibb.co/2WJz1GN/Skjermbilde-2023-08-28-111433.png" alt="Project Outline" title="Laser Gun Game" /></p>

<h2 id="final-project-undecided-factors">Final Project: Undecided Factors</h2>
<p>As we continue to develop our project, several components remain undecided. Here’s a rundown of these aspects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Targets (Toy soldiers or Images)</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>The targets might have a movement mechanism.</li>
      <li><em>Thought:</em> Could a stepper motor be utilized to topple them when hit?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Display</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Choice between an LCD display or a Segment display for point tallying.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Sound</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Do we want to include sound effects?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>CAD Model for the Laser Gun</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>No design has been finalized for the gun.</li>
      <li><em>Strategy:</em> Perhaps modifying an existing gun design would expedite the process?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>CAD Model for Infantry Barricades</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Is there a need for house-like barricades?</li>
      <li><em>Idea:</em> Could we “animate” a door that opens, presenting soldiers to the shooter?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Variety in Soldier Types</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Should one soldier have a unique rank, serving as a ‘Boss’ character?</li>
      <li><em>Advantage:</em> Hitting this character could yield more points.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>2x Arduino in Serial Mode?</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>The Arduino Uno has only 6 IO analog pins. Given that we’re using 4 light-sensitive diodes and need an additional one for serial output to the display, this might pose a challenge. This limits the soldiers to be maximum 4 and 1 for LCD if im to incorporate sound effects.</li>
      <li>To incorporate sound effects, we may need to use two Arduino Unos in tandem. Alternatively, I might find a simpler solution that requires just one Arduino.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Selva Kumar</name><email>selva.kumar@live.no</email></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="initial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Project Initiation &amp; Web Setup]]></summary></entry></feed>